Please come in, senor.
Gracias.
Your husband isn't going to eat?
He already eaten,
senor. He must go to town.
Somehow he looked like a man
who would have to go to town.
Aren't you staying?
No, I've had a
change of plans.
When your husband comes
back with the police,
tell him I'm sorry
I couldn't wait.
Yes, Father.
What are you doing
here with the chickens?
I was just resting
against your shelter.
- This is for animals.
- The house is for men.
Come.
It's nothing.
We will have a
look at it. Come.
Phone Tampico, get the money.
Stop it!
Stop it, you fools, he's got
his hands up! Got his hands!
What is it?
- You were dreaming, my son.
- You shouted in your sleep.
Sorry I disturbed you.
Sleeping men shout in
this fashion in prison,
in the battle lines of armies,
and when we are being hunted.
What do you want me
to do, confess my sins?
I want you to have peace.
Then leave me alone.
As you wish.
Father.
I will dress your arm again.
No doubt the pain was
what disturbed you.
No, no, no. It's not much.
It hardly hurts any.
Well, you saw it yourself.
It's only a little wound.
And yet, Father, here's
the whole trouble.
Because of this wound or
something, I can't move my arm.
I can't lift it.
You mean lift it,
as a man would who was
ordered to surrender?
The police.
Yeah.
They've tracked me for
two days and nights.
They'll be here in the morning.
This is it, the end of the line.
Even the police are
not always so merciless.
You understand, I saw it
happen to another man.
He couldn't lift his arm either.
He stood up in a lonely
place at daybreak.
Somebody shot him.
Somebody who shot-
Come and lie down, my son.
You don't have to
talk about this.
But I do.
I mean, I have to know
the answer, Father,
and there isn't much time.
Began about a year ago.
You might not believe
it to look at me now,
but in those days, I was
running an oil field.
Hey, Lin! Lin Vanner!
I got a flash for you, Lin.
Drive me down to south
field, would you, Herb?
Got a broken bit down there.
Better 90 to the office first.
Know what day this is?
Wednesday.
And the ghost is supposed
to walk this afternoon.
We got payroll trouble?
Not another stick-up?
I thought they were gonna
fly it in like last time.
They couldn't get a
plane! Earl Mahoney.
You know, the guy from
Petroleum Finance Corporation?
He was bringing it up
himself by rail car.
One of those putt putt jobs.
A bank vice prezzie
on a rail car?
He must've been out of his mind.
He had guts, Lin.
He knew how vital it was
after all the trouble we had.
He wanted to be
personally responsible.
Don't take it so hard, Lin.
We've got insurance, you know.
Great but meanwhile what am
I supposed to pay my men with?
Lop washes and seashells?
They like money, moolah.
- You know what I mean.
- Money, let me see.
12 paydays a year,
we get three stick-ups.
- Where's Mahoney now?
- He's in the office.
We'd better step on it, huh?
- Who's this guy?
- Corporal Valdez.
He was in charge of the guard.
- Only guard left?
- That's what they say.
You'd better get Doc
Fellows to take care of him.
He's on his way over.
All I want is a pair
big enough to ride,
and they don't have to fit.
- Hello, Vanner.
- Hi, Mr. Mahoney.
Looks like we're in
a little trouble.
Ah, we'll get that money
back. Every last cent of it.
We'll get this
fellow before dark.
- You're not taking off again?
- You bet I am.
The police coming down has
assigned a mounted squad
to do the tracking, and I
guess they're going to need me.
Anything you want before,
before I take off?
Well, yes.
Frankly, could you give me some
idea of just what happened?
I only got a sketch. I'd
like to make out a report.
Lin, Tampico's calling.
I'll call back
in five minutes.
It was a rough deal.
We were right on that hairpin
turn back at the gorge.
- You know the one?
- Yeah.
Oh, thanks.
This fellow was
track walking there.
Never would've
slowed down for him,
but he had a company badge on
and looked like an American.
About your height, stocky build.
Thought maybe he'd been
sent out to meet us.
Then all of a sudden,
the sky busted open
and the shooting started.
He got three of the guards
with the first burst,
but I fell off the car.
It's probably what
saved your life.
Yeah, I guess so.
Well, I'll put it all in
writing when I get back.
- Good luck.
- So long.
Get Tampico back.
Miss Ware's waiting in there.
Got a cigarette, Herb?
Hi, baby. What are
you doing here?
- I couldn't stay at the ranch.
- This is much too exciting.
Hm. So is having
your pocket picked.
Sometimes I'd settle for that.
Hello? Yes, Mr. Hubble.
Yes, that's it.
The entire payroll.
Yes, I imagine they'll
cancel the insurance
but it can't be helped.
Okay.
Thank you.
The doctor finished
with that corporal?
He's working on him now.
Get a report from him
and ask him to see me
when he gets through, will you?
- Sure.
- Thanks.
Would you like a drink?
Not now. I don't
want to keep you.
Was I going somewhere?
I thought you'd be
going on the posse.
Not me.
- Lin, you don't mean that!
- Sure I mean it.
Well, they'll
think you're chicken.
So I'm chicken.
That stuffed shirt Earl
Mahoney will get all the credit
for catching the thief.
He won't catch him.
- But the posse.
- It's not a posse.
It's an armed police squad
and some gringo.
Besides, posses don't catch
anything but colds in the head.
And this one won't, either,
if they think that guy's
headed for the coast.
Why wouldn't he?
'Cause he's an American.
And what's that
got to do with it?
An American will stay
right on the railroad
where you don't leave a trail.
He can keep on all night that
way, and along toward morning,
he'd cross over to the high
road through some pass.
El Tejon Pass, maybe.
Let's see.
Yeah, that'd be his best out.
It's rough, but once he got
across, he could hit the road.
That's what he'd do, Lin.
If he knows the country well,
and he did know it well.
Oh, he must have
planned this carefully.
You bet he did.
But if you actually
caught this stick-up guy,
you doped it out so brilliantly,
if you brought him
in all by yourself...
I'll admit I'm
crazy enough to wonder
if I've doped it right.
- That's all I wanted to hear.
- Hm?
Bree, would you call my dad's
foreman Pedro at the ranch?
Oh, hold your horses.
- Just one horse, darling.
- The one you're going to ride.
Tell him to catch the quarter
horse, the one dad uses.
- Have you got a gun?
- What would I want a gun for?
Never mind. We'll
get one at the ranch.
Come on, Sheriff. We don't want
to keep that bandit waitin'.
Here we go.
That horse must've been
used to rocky country.
He followed the trail
up the pass all night,
as if he'd had eyes in his feet.
For some reason, I was asking
myself what I was doing there.
I wondered if I hadn't
been out of my mind
to start on this chase
in the first place
just to show off like a
kid turning handsprings
on his girl's front
lawn or something.
This wasn't a game
of cops and robbers.
We were playing for keeps.
It boiled down to a duel between
me and the unknown fellow
waiting up in the rocks or
struggling on ahead of me.
Never had the slightest
doubt that he was there
and that I'd find him,
but I didn't like it.
It was all wrong, somehow.
Maybe I was afraid,
but I don't think I
was afraid for myself.
It was more like being scared
of what was going happen.
The moment which had to come
soon now and would come,
as if it had been
determined long ago
and couldn't be stopped
by any act of mine.
Oh, you see, Father, I'm
trying to justify myself,
explain what happened, though
I never can explain it.
Not in any way that'd make
the answer come out right.
Then, suddenly, I saw the man.
- Get your hands up!
- I got a-
- Both of 'em, over your head!
- I can only get one-
- Get 'em up!
I can't, you...
Some posse man. Shooting
a guy with his hands up.
Told you to put 'em both up.
I couldn't. My arm's busted.
That's what I was
trying to tell you.
I didn't hear you.
Where'd I hit you?
Ah, it's nothin'.
Maybe I'm lucky at that.
Pick that coffee
pot up, will you?
Hey, didn't you used
to work for Bolsa Grande?
- Sure, I was a rigger.
- Sam Tevlin's my name.
I thought so.
- And I know you, Mr.
- Vanner, and you don't act
no different now than when
you were down at the plant.
All right. Pull
yourself together.
I'm gonna stash your
stuff and take you back.
- What for?
- You know what for!
I never took that
payroll, if that's what you mean.
- How'd you know about it?
- Well, I-
- All right, we'll
talk about that later.
Well, if I took
it, where is it?
Did I hide it out
somewhere? Have I got it on?
Hey, why don't you search me?
If you've got it on
you, we'll find it.
If you've hidden it out,
we'll find that, too.
All in due time. Come on.
Come on.
As we started down, I think
I felt weaker than he did.
I was shaky and sick because
I knew in my heart
I'd shot too soon.
I hadn't given him a chance
to explain about his arm.
I felt pity for him.
Oh, easy. That's it.
You've been sitting at a
desk too much, Mr. Posse Man.
You're kinda soft in the belly.
I didn't figure I'd have
to pack you onto my back.
Oh, we're buddies, aren't we?
One pal don't mind
helping another.
Especially when he shot
him with his hands up.
That's a lie and you know it.
Do I?
Come on.
Maybe I oughtta
pack you on my back.
Car waiting for you, huh?
Yeah, could be.
I don't suppose there's
any use telling you again,
I didn't take that payroll.
You'll have to tell
that to the proper authorities.
That's about what
I figured you'd say.
Look, Mr. Vanner.
If those company guards
get a hold of me now,
I haven't got a chance.
Give me a break, will you?
Turn me loose right here.
I'm not so beat up
that I won't make out,
if you let me take the horse.
Can't do it, Tevlin.
I was half tempted to
give him the chance,
but it was too late.
I had to see this through
the way I'd started.
Boss, you sure
did a great job!
You certainly did, and say,
did you hear about the reward?
Reward?
Yeah, the head office
put it up last night,
right after you
left, 2,000 bucks!
- Congratulations, boss.
- Nice going, Lin.
Boy, oh boy, that helps.
Hey, 2,000 bucks!
Never ride in a pal's
boots unless he wears 12D.
Well, my boy, I understand
you're to be congratulated.
You've done a fine job.
Well, I'm not even
sure he's the right man,
but at least he's
suspect number one.
Lieutenant, my company
has a vital interest
in this matter.
Would you object if I asked
the prisoner a few questions?
No, go ahead, senor,
but don't take too long.
- Oh, no.
- Where is he, Clark?
In the back office, boss.
Well, let's go and see if
we can find something out.
Thank you, Lieutenant.
Hey, what's going in there?
I suppose you'd call
it a cross examination.
That's your man,
all right, Lieutenant.
He doesn't feel
like talking, but,
I can positively identify him.
My department will
check it out, Mr. Mahoney.
Good.
How is he?
In bad shape.
I'm gonna give him a hypo. Will
you stay with him a minute?
Don't suppose
there's use
telling you again.
I...
I didn't take that payroll.
It's cold.
Cold in here.
Better?
Mother. Mother.
Your mother will be
here. She's on her way.
Thank you.
That cross
examination must've been
a form of torture
in his condition.
That wasn't what killed him.
What, then?
A bullet, right there.
Why, I thought
that only nicked him.
No, no. It punctured
the pulmonary artery.
He bled internally.
Well, I'm sorry, baby, but
I hadn't heard of any reward
when I went after this guy
and I don't have to be paid
for bringing him in.
Why you keep saying
"paid"? It's not paid.
It's just a sort of prize,
an honor you're entitled to.
Oh, Lin.
Think what $2,000
can mean to us.
Well, I'm not
going to take it.
Call it sentiment or
superstition or anything you like.
I'd call it insanity.
You wouldn't borrow
money from the company,
and I could understand that,
but now that they want to
give you some, you refuse.
Can't you see it from my angle?
How do you expect me to feel?
I don't mean to be rude,
but I don't think
this is your affair.
I thought it was.
Seems to me I remember
starting you on this, right?
Yes, you started me, but...
Well, now it's something else.
Something between me and-
- Your precious conscience?
If you hadn't been
cleared at the inquest,
it might be different.
I won't take it, Lin.
I've taken a lot and
tried to understand,
but this is just a
little bit too much.
You mean you're
breaking our engagement?
No, you are, with
this crazy attitude.
I've waited and hoped and tried
to see your point of view.
I didn't know I was being taken
and you never meant to marry me.
All this talk about
money was just an excuse.
What you wanted was an alibi.
Any reason was all right, as
long as you could put me off!
Well, you've got your way and
now I'm not changing my mind!
This time it's
finished! We're through!
- You're yelling.
- I will yell!
Oh, Lin, what's
happened to us?
I don't...
I don't know, baby.
I guess we both found out
at the same time, didn't we?
We'd never get along.
I just love you to pieces, Lin,
but I know I'll never understand
you as long as I live.
Remember, it's right
here on this table.
I wish you'd keep it.
That's
very gallant of you,
just the right thing to
say, but I'm leaving it.
You might need the
money to put in
a blind man's cup or something.
Tampico 324.
It's Mr. Vanner
calling Mr. Hubble.
If he's not there,
please try him at home.
Thanks.
Hello?
Oh, Mr. Hubble.
This is Lin Vanner.
I'm very sorry to disturb you
at this time of night, but...
Yes, I believe it is urgent.
Well, sir, I hate to
put you in a spot,
but I'm resigning my
position with the company.
That's right.
I know it is sudden, but...
No, sir.
Where to, senor?
Just give me about 100
pesos worth of ticket.
In what direction, senor?
You name it and I'll go
there, on the first train out.
Do I understand you
wish a change of scenery?
Any place will do?
That's right.
- How would you like Los Santos?
- It's a nice little place.
- Los Santos?
- Yes.
Today, we ship a coffin there.
For such shipments, a
ticket must be bought,
and this one has been paid for,
too, according to the rules.
But today, no one is using it.
All right, I'll
take it. Thanks.
- You're welcome, senor.
- You've saved me trouble, too.
Would you be kind and give
these to the baggage agent
at Los Santos?
- I'll do that.
- Good luck, senor.
I knew there
was only one dead man
who could be going from
La Mancha that day,
but I didn't care.
I'd accept that much
from Sam Tevlin.
My transportation to a new life.
After all, we'd been
traveling companions before.
A new life.
I figured that was ahead of me.
Nothing behind.
I was a lucky guy,
I told myself.
Why not?
I was still young enough,
reasonably strong,
and this new life
could be a lot of fun.
All I had to do was hand some
papers to a baggage agent,
and then the last thread
that held me to the past
would be gone.
I could go anywhere I felt
like, do anything I wanted.
Los Santos!
But then I had another thought.
Someone had paid to have
Sam's body sent home,
and the person who had
paid would meet the train.
Well, whoever it was, I
didn't want to see them.
I was finished with
the whole business.
I'd just had enough of it.
I made up my mind to made tracks
getting away from that station.
Senor?
Tequila.
Si, senor.
- As I live and breathe!
- Put it there, Lin!
Carlos, you old son of
a gun!
Oh, you're getting
a little fat.
Oh, what is a few
pounds between friends?
And you know something?
I will always buy a
drink for a doggone hero.
Let's go sit at the table, eh?
You know, I was just
reading about you.
A guy on the crew sent me this.
It was in the Veracruz paper.
Keep it
for your scrapbook.
Didn't know you had it in you.
And here's luck.
Luck? Oh, that
is what we have.
Plenty of it, Lin.
Biggest blinking oil strike
in years, right here,
only 50 miles from Los Santos.
Maybe I ought to cut
myself a slice of it.
Oh, there'll be
enough for everybody.
Man, you should have
seen that first gosher.
Gosher? What is a gosher?
With or without the accent,
it's 50,000 barrels a day.
All high-gravity stuff.
Hey, Lin, why don't you come
and have a look at it
with me tomorrow, huh?
Oh, compadre, you
got yourself a date.
Bueno.
So I took a job
in a few field.
After a couple of
months, I quit.
I kept thinking I had
to get back to that town
and find somebody.
Crazy enough, I
couldn't seem to think
of anyone but this person.
As you've guessed it, Father,
it was the woman I'd seen
for a few seconds on a
railway station platform.
Tevlin's widow.
I'd found out that
much about her.
But then I found
out where she lived.
And finally, I hitched
a ride out of town.
That was the first
time I saw the ranch.
Neat and comfortable enough,
and yet it had that sorry
kind of a look a place gets
when there's no man
to take care of it.
You know, that it looked
different once when there was hope
when people started out to
build something, and then, we",
they let go or were
defeated in their purpose.
This was where a
woman lived her life,
and I wondered what the power
was that had drawn me there.
My share in her secret,
or was it just herself,
her beauty or her personality?
Which was really unknown to
me and only half guessed at.
I hadn't thought of any special
way to explain my visit.
Figured I'd just knock on the
door and see what happened.
Who is it?
Are you Mrs. Tevlin?
That's right.
Won't you come in?
Sit down.
Oh, thanks.
Your name, please?
Brown.
Lindley Brown.
We've see each other
before, haven't we, Mr. Brown?
No, I don't think so.
I hadn't expected
anyone so soon.
- In answer to the ad.
- Oh?
You
understood the terms?
I can't pay wages, but
I'll share the profits
after the stock is
rounded up and sold.
Oh, I see. I wasn't
quite sure about the wages.
Oh, I thought that was clear.
It's right here.
"Foreman for ranch co-op."
You must have understood it.
Oh, that'll be
all right, I think.
We run between
300 and 400 head.
The range is good and we
have a nice calf crop.
I have one Indian
vaquero helping me,
but I've no way to round
up, brand, and sell.
I should imagine it'd
be a little hard to keep house
and ride a herd, too.
Yes, even for a person
capable of handling livestock,
which I'm not.
I've often thought of giving
up, going back to the States.
When I had to decide,
I always try once more.
Hang on a little longer.
My husband and I bought
this place with savings
and he used to work
in his spare time.
Now my husband is dead.
Well, I think you're
quite right to keep it.
Place of your own can
mean a great deal.
My husband used to work
for the oil companies.
Have you ever worked in
the oil fields, Mr. Brown?
Oh, yes, I have.
But where I grew up, oil
and cattle were a team,
nudging each other for
the same hunk of ground.
I can pass myself off for
a cowboy when I have to.
Get a load of those
boots. He's no cowboy.
- Mike, this is Mr. Brown.
- This is my son, Michael.
- Hi, Michael.
- Hello.
Mike, you're right about
these boots, they're no good,
but I've had the other
kind, no kidding.
And I can roll my own
cigarettes when I have to.
I'd want to be quite sure
that you understood the work
and that you were
confident to do it.
Things have run down
here. It won't be easy.
I'd like to try.
Is he gonna stay, Ma?
We haven't decided yet.
Well, if he is,
I'm moving out.
I'll tell you, Michael, I'm
looking for a place to work
and your mother wants someone
to help her the way you do.
Now, wouldn't it be
all right with you
if I just sort of hung
around and helped your mom?
It's okay with me, if
that's what you want, Mom.
All right. We'll try
it and see how it goes.
I suppose you have to get
your things from town.
I can do
that this evening.
I'll show you the
room you can use.
So, now I understood.
She was stuck for somebody
to work the ranch.
She naturally would
be, with Sam gone.
That ad in the local paper
must've been a last resort
for her, but for me, it was
a chance sent from heaven.
I was only sure of one thing.
My being here had nothing to
do with the late Mr. Tevlin.
Only with Mrs. Tevlin.
I'd come because I'd seen a
woman on a station platform.
And now that I'd talked to her,
I'd made up my mind I
was going to be near her,
even if Sam Tevlin
came back from the dead
to try and stop me.
Why, hi, pal. How you
feeling this morning?
Okay. I always feel okay.
Swell. That little
paint your horse?
Yep, what'd you catch him
for? He likes to be let loose.
Maybe you'd want to
slap a saddle on him
and ride out with me.
- I'll tell you why I can't 90.
- There's Indians around here.
No kidding. Sometimes,
they attack.
Then I have to take
care of Ma, you see?
Sure. Well, you do that.
So long, Mike. See you tonight.
So long.
Did Mr. Brown ask
you to go with him?
- I couldn't 90!
- There's an attack!
So we found some tracks
and we followed 'em, and,
pretty soon Mike here heard
this little bull calf bellowing.
Just moaning, like he
said, and gosh awful.
He was dragged
off with his mammy
in a little canyon where
the spring had dried up.
We got him out of there,
though, didn't we?
Next week, I'm gonna dam
that creek so there'll be
some water up that way
when the bad months come.
Lin says when enough water
gets in it, I can swim there.
That's fine, but right now,
it's getting pretty
near somebody's bedtime.
Aw gee, Ma.
If you want to be a vaquero,
you've got to take time
out to go to sleep.
Can't I fool around
with Lin a little while?
Not tonight, honey.
Mr. Brown has some work to do.
You go along now.
I'll be in later to
read you that story.
I was going to help him
with that bridle he's making
but I guess it'll keep.
It will have to keep.
I've something else
I want you to do.
Will you come with me, please?
Sure.
I had the
colt in here today
and he broke through the fence.
I'd like you to fix it.
Okay, I'll start first
thing in the morning.
I want it done now.
Well, isn't it a little late
to begin wrangling fences?
When there's work to be done,
you'll just have to do it,
if you expect to stay here.
She had a real genius
for concocting that
kind of assignment.
Every night after work,
and day times, too,
if I had 10 minutes to spare,
she'd come up with something
new, and generally,
she'd find some excuse to
be around and watch me.
If she could've stood
over me with a whip,
that would've pleased
her better still.
I almost quit 100 times, but
always managed to hold out,
because I knew something
was boiling inside her,
eating her up, and I wanted
to find out what it was.
So I took everything
she handed out
and waited for the next move.
Hi, pal.
Wanna try?
Sure, come on.
How do you put your fingers?
Well, let's see. First one
would be about like that.
That's pretty good. A
little farther back.
Press harder.
You do it.
Tired already?
All right. What'll it be?
The one you were playing.
Oh, one about the
doggies. You like that?
Did you ever go to Wyoming?
No, but I always
had a hankering to.
If you went,
would you come back?
Sure, you bet I would.
Chances are I'm
not going anyway.
What's "dead"?
I mean, what does it mean, dead?
Dead?
Well, that's when
you're not here anymore.
When you stop
being what you are.
When you start to
be something else?
I guess so, Mike. I don't
know much about those things.
Most people don't.
- My mom does.
- Does she?
Yeah. She told me about it.
My dad's not coming
back anymore.
I'm sorry.
- Oh, that's okay.
- He's in heaven.
Heaven. What a place.
I bet you nothing
happens up there much.
Supposed to be all right.
Those angels, they
look like ladies.
Are there men angels, too?
There are both kinds, I guess.
They have spears.
Sure they do.
I saw it in a picture.
I had a spear once
but I lost it.
Michael.
I'm out here with Lin, Mom.
Come in, dear. It's bedtime.
I'm coming.
Doggone, I wish I
hadn't lost that spear.
I lost my bow and arrow, too.
It was a swell one.
My dad made it for me.
When he comes back, he'll...
Well, he's not coming
back. I told you that.
Can you make a bow and arrow?
Well, I guess I
could. I could sure try.
Will you tomorrow?
Well, yeah.
Yeah, I will.
Gee, thanks, Lin.
Okay.
You'd better go on in now.
Okay. You won't forget
the bow and arrow, will you?
No, I won't forget.
You're a pal. Well, goodnight.
Goodnight, son.
Son.
There I was, moving into
something I'd never bargained for.
I was picking up a
ready-made family for myself
and loving it.
All except one thing.
Ellen wouldn't change
her manner to me,
at least when we were alone.
In front of Mike,
she was nice as pie.
Can I go out and
shoot now, Mom?
Sure.
- You coming, Lin?
- In a minute.
I'm fixing to help your
mother with these dishes.
Dishes. Holy smoke.
I can make out
without help, thank you.
How long do we have
to keep on this way?
I don't know what you mean.
The way we are now, like
strangers mashed together
against their will, not
knowing what to do about it.
What would you
suggest we do about it?
Well, we could act like
a human once in a while.
Like at the table, you
never say a word to me,
except " pass this, pass that".
When the meal's through,
no time for anything.
I go to work, Mike goes
to play, and you...
Could sit around and talk a
little bit. Now, people do that.
Just pour an extra
cup of coffee.
Or if you don't like
that, we could go uptown.
Sure, in the evenings.
We could walk around the
plaza and listen to the band,
look in the shop windows.
Maybe even take you into one
of those old time movies.
Now, Mike would like that.
We have no money
to waste on shows.
But we have to do
something, don't you see?
Even if we fight and
yell and throw things.
What should we fight about?
About anything!
At least we'd
prove that we're alive.
This way, it's nothing.
The days go by.
I don't know where they
go or what's wrong.
It's like a sickness or like
being goofy or something.
We just stand still.
You feel it, too.
You know what I mean.
Why, even have would be-
Hate?
- What do you know about hate?
- Well, not much, thank god.
Hate can be sweeter
than anything.
You've hurt yourself.
It's just a scratch.
Can we go swimming, Ma?
I thought you were having
a big Indian war today.
It's Sunday. You said we
could swim at the dam Sundays.
Oh, you can't go alone,
dear, and I can't go with you.
- Aw gee, but Rico can swim.
- He's going to teach me.
Lin has the irrigation ditch
all made and it's real deep.
All right, 90 on.
Gee, thanks!
I don't blame 'em.
Oh, this air, wow!
It's always that
way this season.
Short of going
swimming with the kids,
I don't know what to
do about it myself,
unless I use the family
swimming pool here,
like Mike did yesterday.
You're most welcome
to it, I'm sure.
You mean I have your gracious
permission to dunk myself?
You know I don't
care what you do.
Oh, you're too kind. You
can't miss a chance like this.
Yoo-hoo!
You know, I was working
one time on a tramp steamer
down on the Caribbean
and we were quarantined
for a couple of weeks
in the company port.
It was a case of
typhus on board.
Well, maybe we were lucky or
it wasn't typhus or something.
Anyway, when we put out
to sea again, the captain
stopped the ship and let us
all go over side for a swim,
and it was a great feeling.
And you know something?
Today was just as good.
Yes, sir, that little old barrel
is all right for a Sunday dip.
Imagine you had more
room in the Caribbean.
Are you, uh, you
through with this?
You can take it to
your room and read it.
Oh, no. It's
fine right here, thanks.
Ellen?
Ellen, will you listen
to me for a minute?
Listening to you is
just a waste of time.
You weren't wasting your
time when you went to my room
and looked through my things.
My wallet, for instance.
You'd seen me at the station.
You wanted to know if
my real name was Brown.
You found out it wasn't.
I found
out you were the man
who murdered my husband.
Murdered?
That's a pretty big word.
Generally, before you
hang that on a man,
you investigate what he's done.
Most times, a lawyer
presents the evidence,
a jury considers it, and
a judge passes sentence.
What are you, judge, jury,
and prosecuting attorney,
all rolled into one?
Did Sam Tevlin
have a judge, jury,
and prosecuting attorney?
I was working for a company
and he'd stolen money
from that company.
At least, that's what everyone
believed, and I did, too.
Did you believe it?
What made you so sure?
Did Sam tell you he was a thief,
or did you forget to give
him time to tell you?
Well, there wasn't time for...
Go on.
Well, what do
you know about it?
You speak as if
you'd been there.
You were the one who
started asking questions.
Well, let me ask you something.
Why did you shoot Sam
when he had his hands up?
He only had one
up. I yelled at him.
But nobody knew
that. Nobody except-
- No one except you, Mr. Vanner.
You and Sam.
But Sam's dead, so that
leaves you all by yourself.
And you're quite right.
There was no word about
it in the clipping I read.
Would you like to know
how I found that out?
I found out from Sam.
They sent him home to me.
You should remember that.
You got a free ride with him.
Well, I looked at Sam's body.
A wife is apt to do that if
her husband is sent home dead
and she doesn't know
what killed him.
I saw where the bullet went in,
just below the
muscle of the chest.
His arm was raised when it hit,
because the muscle dropped
over the hole and sealed it up.
That's why he bled internally.
Oh yes, Mr. Vanner.
I know how my husband died.
You were a great hero.
You were very brave that
morning at daybreak.
Ellen.
Won't you please go now?
Ellen, everything
you've said is true.
I think I shot too soon.
Oh, he yelled something at me,
but I couldn't make
out what it was and...
Well, I thought he was playing
a trick on me and so I-
- You got the shakes.
You were a coward and you killed
because you were a coward.
Believe me, it wasn't that.
Men who get the shakes
shouldn't go on posse rides.
They should clean pigsties.
They should crawl in the dirt.
I've been doing those
things. I thought you knew.
I'll send you your
share of the money
when the stock is sold.
I can get somebody else
to round up for me.
We were talking about Sam.
I was with him when he died
and he didn't ask for you.
He asked for his mother.
What's the point
of telling me that?
I'm telling you because
this wifely loyalty
doesn't fool me a bit!
Sam didn't think of you
when he was dying alone,
groping for one
thought or feeling
that would help or comfort him.
Don't you think most men
would turn to their wives,
under such circumstances?
I don't know. It'd
depend on the man.
And the woman, and the
way they'd lived together.
Oh, it's a small thing, might
not mean anything at all,
but it's part of the feeling
I've had about you and Sam.
It's hard to put into words,
but it seems to me you
two were strangers.
Is that wrong?
Oh, people can be married
and even have a child
and buy a ranch,
the way you did,
and never like each other
much, or even know each other.
From the looks of this place,
I don't believe he spent
a year all told here
as your husband.
It was more fun to buck the
oilfields for a bankroll
and make love to Tampico
dance hall girls.
Isn't that about the way
it was between you two?
Yes, that's just
the way it was,
but some women would
kill you for saying so.
But not you, people
get punished for killing,
and you don't figure
to get punished.
You operate from your
brains, not your feelings.
You've let me work
here, knowing who I was,
because you needed me.
Besides, what fun
it was to ride me,
when I had no
comeback, wasn't it?
- It was sweet.
- It was wonderful.
Yes and the best of it was
I couldn't hit you in the face
and walk out on you for six
months, the way Sam used to.
You didn't learn to
hate men from me,
or from anything you
found out about me.
You learned from Sam.
You've been saving
something up against all men
and you've enjoyed
letting it out on me.
Well, you've won, Mrs. Tevlin.
Our partnership is washed
up and you may keep my share
of the profits, if any,
with my compliments.
Is that the way
you say goodbye?
Unless I'm saying hello.
Hello, then.
I don't know what
love is, Father,
unless it's one person's
recognition of another,
or one great experience that
breaks down the walls of self.
Well, we had it, Ellen and I.
We'd begun at the place
where most people never get.
The final explanations.
People pay for
such explanations,
but there are also rewards.
Yes, Father.
Well, we found the
greatest reward of all.
Our marriage.
Amen.
I could hardly
follow the priest's words
because I kept thinking,
"She's mine now.
She's mine."
That day, I was sure the
devils that had haunted me
since I shot Sam Tevlin
were gone for good,
but they weren't through
with me yet, Father,
as I found out.
- Give me some rice.
- Not now.
I want a big handful.
Oh, Michael. You were
a wonderful best man.
Yeah, thanks for
standing up with me, chum.
Oh, that's okay. I
got something for you.
- Yeah?
- Good luck, compadre.
Oh, thanks.
- Here.
- What's that?
Ellen, look at the wedding
present Mike got us!
Oh, they're beautiful.
- Can I try 'em on now?
- Oh, they'll fit.
I copped one of your
old boots for size.
Oh, let me try 'em
on anyway. Let's see.
Here. Over here.
Well, Ellen, good luck.
Thank you, Carlos.
I'm so happy.
You'll get
something out of that.
Just perfect.
I guess I'll see you later.
Oh, we'll see you
tonight at the party.
I'm a real cowboy now.
Absolutely perfect.
- You like the butterflies?
- They've got real ones.
Yeah. They're the best looking
pair of boots I ever saw.
- How about that?
- They're beautiful.
Come here.
What's that I hear
about a party?
It's a surprise.
Every wedding has to
have a party afterwards.
Have to have a procession.
Procession? But who's coming?
I don't know. Juan
invited most of them.
Oh-ho! That's the
country club set.
Think they're
having a good time?
- Wonderful.
- Oh, I'm glad.
Well, Juan's a little careless
with that Milwaukee champagne.
Gracias.
All right, compadre, you are
through. Carlos takes over.
Oh, take it easy,
bridesmaid. This is our job.
Go, little one. Go hold
hands with your husband.
You're an angel, Carlos.
I could use a
little hand holding.
I hid out two plates
of food for us in the house.
- You're a smart woman.
- Hm, and a good cook.
Oh, well, wait a
minute. I did the cooking.
You did the carving.
Oh. Oh, yeah.
Our first party.
We're livin'.
People say that for a joke,
and yet it can mean so much.
You were the one
who made me realize
I'd been alive without living.
Even the hate I thought
I had for you was a lie.
I couldn't let myself
admit I loved you.
Do you?
I feel as if tonight, all
the nights and days ahead of us
were a wedding present from you.
You've helped me,
too. You know that.
How?
You made me quit running away.
Were you running when
you first came here?
Why?
You know why.
But not now. You're
not running now.
You don't blame
yourself for anything.
No, I don't think so.
Yet here's the funny twist.
I only thought of it tonight.
I'm in Sam's shoes,
don't you see?
It's as if a wheel were turning
in a circle or something.
Sam's wife, Sam's kid.
But...
Then you haven't stopped
running, darling.
Not until you know Sam's
shoes are on Sam's feet.
You're wearing boots from a
little boy that loves you,
and you're married to a girl
who never really was Sam's wife
just as you told me.
She's really yours.
There is no past.
Nothing's going to happen.
Just the two of us together now.
What's with those children?
Doesn't sound like playing.
You're right. That's a scrap.
Hey!
Hey! Hey, Mike!
Mike, Mike!
Hey, take it easy, will ya?
Well, well, what's it all about?
Honey, maybe you'd better
take him back with the others.
Go on.
Go on, Pablito.
Come here. Tell me about it.
What happened?
Oh, this is just
between us chums.
Nothin'.
Well, something
must have happened.
They said somethin'.
Uh-huh. About you?
About your mom or me?
About my dad.
While he was
playing the moccasins game
with those kids, he heard one
of them say he was the son
of that bandito Tevlin.
Oh, how terrible.
I was hoping he wouldn't have
to hear about it like that.
How would we put it
to sound any better?
I don't know. I suppose
he'll have to be told someday.
What shall we tell him?
The truth.
That his father
was a stick-up man?
I didn't think we knew
the truth about that.
Oh, Lin, you can't turn back
now. You can't undo the past.
No, but you can
find out facts.
If there's blame, you can
put it where it belongs.
Oh, I've had this on
my back for a year now.
The way I had Sam when I
took him down the pass.
Why should he have stolen
money? He wasn't a criminal.
He could always get a
job in the oil fields.
In fact, I'll bet he was rail
hitching back to Bolsa Grande
looking for a job when the
payroll car caught up with him,
if it did.
And another thing, why was
the posse and the police
dragged through every cut
and cane break between here
and the coast instead of
the mountains, where I went?
At the time, I thought it was
just stupid and yet it seemed
wrong to me somehow, even
while I was riding after him.
I'm sure someone in that posse
never meant for
him to be caught.
There's a man alive somewhere
who took that payroll
and caused Sam's death,
and I want him to pay.
You can't forget, can you?
All right.
I don't want this
hanging over our heads.
Go and do it, and
then come back to me.
So I traveled back
the way I'd come,
only this time, I
paid for my ticket.
I went to the company files
and looked up everything
they had about the holdup.
Oh, by the way, do you happen
to remember the name of
that guard, you know,
the one that was wounded?
Well, there ought to
be a medical report
on him there, hadn't there?
Mm. Oughta be
in here some place.
Valdez.
That's it. That's it.
Here we are.
Corporal Valdez.
You don't
remember me, do you?
You're not a stranger, senor.
But I, since my wound,
my memory's not so good.
I know about that wound.
I was an official at
the Bolsa Grande company
when you were brought in.
I was the one who sent for
the doctor to take care you.
You stayed?
Ah, Si.
Si!
Mr. Vanner.
Senor Valdez, I'd like to
have a little talk with you.
Couldn't we sit down
and rest awhile?
Si, senor.
Would you like a cigarette?
Muchas gracias.
I'm glad you've
made such a recovery,
but I have serious news for you.
My pension. Has it stopped?
Oh, I don't know
anything about that,
but the case concerning the
hold-up has been reopened.
I'd like to ask you
a few questions.
- It's a long time ago. Mr.
- Vanner, my memory is bad.
Well, I'll try to refresh
it. Now, come on, sit down.
Let's see, you were assigned
with three men as an escort
for Earl Mahoney, who
was bringing the money.
Yes, but that-
- In the mountains, the car
came up with an American
who was walking the tracks.
The reports say he had a Tommy
gun. Now try to remember.
Did the gringo have the gun,
or did he take it from
one of the guards?
He had it with him,
senor.
Track walking
with a machine gun.
Strange nobody noticed
that when you slowed down.
A Tommy gun doesn't
fit in a man's pocket.
He was hiding it maybe
underneath his clothes.
Oh, I tell you wrong. He grab
it from one of the guards.
Yes, I think he did that!
You're lying, Valdez.
Not this American, but
somebody else had that gun,
and that person used it on you.
You weren't meant to be found
alive, and when you were,
somebody warned you
to keep your mouth.
Warned you and paid you,
which is how you got that
pension you spoke of a minute ago.
Senor Vanner-
- And since then, you've
been afraid of every shadow,
haven't you?
Even had bad dreams about it.
Dreams where you can
see the man with the gun
firing on the guard, your
companeros, and on you.
Who are you protecting, Valdez?
Who is the man with the gun?
Who took the Bolsa
Grande payroll?
I must...
I must ring the
bell at the mission.
All right. I'll wait.
I pitied Valdez for his
insane act, but he'd left
my plan of operations
hanging as high as he was.
He'd been my last, and
in fact, my only witness,
and he was dead.
All I could do now was
figure out another angle,
even though I knew it
was a crazy gamble.
Strictly a shot in the dark.
Nobody's allowed
to drink in here.
What do you wish, senor?
10 minutes in your files.
I regret exceedingly,
that will be impossible.
Perhaps you need an opener.
I'm sorry. There are
positively no exceptions.
That's disappointing.
This beer is warm. I will
get some ice, for 10 minutes.
This is the file
index. It is lock.
The keys, you understand,
are in the desk drawer.
I forbid you to use them.
I'd like to see Mr. Mahoney.
Step inside, sir.
Mr. Mahoney in?
He's busy.
All right. I'll wait.
You state your
business, Mister?
Okay, have a talk with
him and get back to me.
I want a yes or
no by 12 o'clock.
You'll have it.
You wish to see me?
Aye, Mr. Mahoney.
Lin Vanner! Long time no see.
- How've you been?
- Doing fair.
Maybe a little better.
No complaints at all.
So I noticed. "Earl
C. Mahoney Enterprises".
What's on your mind?
I...
Come on inside.
I don't want to be disturbed.
Quite a little
place you've got here.
Not bad, is it?
I picked it up awhile back from
the estate of General Ibera.
Sit down.
You know, it was kind
of you to drop in.
Won't you have a spot of cognac?
No, thanks. I'll come
right to the point.
Got a little statement here
I'd like you to glance over.
Not trying to
raise a little dough, are you?
No, just straightening
out some facts.
Facts concerning
the payroll hold-up
at the Bolsa Grande
company about a year ago.
Tell me something.
Yeah.
Have you lost your mind?
Why? Is there some inaccuracy?
Inaccuracy?
You state here that
I, Earl C. Mahoney,
planned and executed the
Bolsa Grande payroll robbery.
That's right.
That I myself
machine gunned six men
and wounded Corporal Valdez.
That I then hid out the money,
and put the blame on
an American oil worker
whom we'd met track
walking in the mountains.
Sam Tevlin.
You haven't figured on him,
I'll admit, but finding him,
the way you did, worked
like a charm for your plan.
You know, I get a
kick out of this.
What did you do, dream
it up all by yourself?
Not quite. I
did some studying.
As an oil operator, you were
running into tough luck.
Your finance company
was almost broke.
You had an option on a new field
that you thought would save you,
but you didn't have the
money to take it up.
Two days after the
robbery, you took it up,
and that was the deal
that made you rich.
Here's a photostat in the
memorandum from your own files.
So, one day I had no
money, the next I had some.
What's so unusual about that?
You think for
evidence like this,
I'm going sign your confession,
or whatever you call it?
Yes, I think you will.
You've got guts. I like that.
What's the deal, Vanner?
I want to clear
a dead man's name.
For clearing dead men's
names, I pay 5,000 pesos.
That's tops.
Not enough.
10.
This deal won't cost
you a cent, Mahoney,
except the price of a
trip out of the country,
after you've signed that paper.
I suggest you move fast, and
once you're out of Mexico,
you stay out.
This country doesn't like
Americans who ignore her laws.
And if I don't sign?
Think I'll change my
mind about that brandy.
Help yourself.
You know, Vanner,
you're a tough man,
But you don't leave
me much choice.
I guess I'll have to
play along with you.
Get up.
Come on, get up!
Sure, I'd killed
him in self defense,
and I should've called the
cops and given myself up,
tried to make the story stick.
It would've been a
simple thing to do.
I even thought of it, I guess,
and yet I couldn't do it.
I couldn't think straight
anymore, except to make sure
that I had something to
fight with, if I got caught,
and I didn't intend
getting caught.
Hey, he doesn't
want to be disturbed.
- He told me to come back.
- Oh, you know best?
Yes.
Your hat, sir.
Mr. Mahoney, I...
Senora.
I figured I could work
up to the mountain trails
and find my way
home across country.
I wanted to see
Ellen and Mike again.
Maybe we could
work something out.
Some way to salvage our lives.
But the next day,
the police picked up my
trail and cut me off.
I was sure by this time they
must have the ranch staked out.
- Senora, you understand.
- Now we must search the house.
Very well.
They've been watching
us for a week.
Why did they choose
tonight to search for him?
Because they think
they know something,
but they don't know enough.
Where is he?
When they leave,
go to the priest hut
at the foot of the mountains.
Oh, Father, can't you
do something for my arm?
My son, if I could
help you, I would be glad to.
I know.
We talked all night.
It was coming
daybreak then, too.
The day when I...
When you?
When I made my mistake.
Look.
They are here.
Senor Vanner!
For a man of your intelligence,
that is a poor decision.
I want to live, Father,
whether it's for 30
years or 30 seconds.
If I go out there, I'll die.
Come out, Vanner!
Vanner!
Do not shoot!
That's someone with him.
It's a woman.
So that is where
you want to be,
but take this message to him.
He must give himself
up in two minutes
or we will shoot again,
whether you are there or not.
It's Ellen!
Oh, Lin.
Oh, Ellen, you
shouldn't have come here.
You've done just what they
wanted, given them a hostage.
It doesn't matter. You've
got to give yourself up.
That's something I can't do.
But it's the only
way. Please listen.
- Oh, you're hurt.
- It's nothing.
He cannot raise
his arm to surrender.
Oh, Lin.
Well, then you've got to
tell them what's happened.
Make them understand
that you're wounded.
It's no use, Ellen.
Darling, you've got to listen.
I know you killed
Mahoney in self defense.
I'm sure of it.
You can make them believe
it, too. You can get justice.
No! Don't you understand
what's happened?
It's the full circle.
This was in the cards.
It had to come out this way,
right from the very first.
It's just a scratch, and even
if I take my arm this way now,
I can't lift it,
I can't move it.
I can't!
- Vanner!
- Your time is up!
Get over there.
Get over there!
- Oh, Father, what can we do?
- He wants to destroy himself.
Yes, and it's not his wound.
He feels he must destroy himself
because of something
he has done.
It has happened to many
men. I have seen it.
This is in his mind.
I'm going out!
Ellen!
Are you hurt? Are you all right?
I wasn't hit. I fell.
Your arm.
You used your arm.
This is the answer. We
haven't lost, we've won.
We can live.
We can be together again.
But have we won?
If I...
If I go outside...
If you want to be with
your wife and son again,
you must try.
I'm coming out!
Put up your hand!
- Come with us.
- Have faith, my son.
Come.